Robert E. Lee Papers WLU.Coll.0064
Washington and Lee University, University Library Special Collections and Archives
- Letters to and about Robert E. Lee, 1837-1870 (Box 7-12A)
  - Letters to and about Robert E. Lee, 1866-02-01-1866-05-31 (Box 7A, Folder 36-63)
    - Correspondences, 1866-03-26-1866-03-31 (Box 7A, Folder 50)
      - Edward Long Hedden to Robert E. Lee, 1866-03-30; Hedden, Edward Long, 1828-1893 (Box 7A, Folder 50)
        Engraving--Printing; Lee, Robert E. (Robert Edward), 1807-1870
      - S. J. Henderson to Robert E. Lee, 1866-03-27; Henderson, S. J. (Box 7A, Folder 50)
        This letter to Robert E. Lee is from S. J. Henderson. Henderson and Judge Charles Lewis McConnell have heard Lee plans to write a book on the American Civil War. Henderson and McConnell ask to have publishing agency in Kentucky for Lee's book.
        Publishers and publishing; Lee, Robert E. (Robert Edward), 1807-1870; McConnell, Charles Lewis, Judge, 1825-1906; Big Sandy Coal, Oil and Mining Company
      - Sargent, Wilson & Hinkle to Robert E. Lee, 1866-03-31; Sargent, Wilson & Hinkle (Box 7A, Folder 50)
        This letter to Robert E. Lee is from the book publisher Sargent, Wilson and Hinkle. This letter asks Lee for his approval of McGuffey Eclectic Readers books on the American Civil War.
        McGuffey's first-sixth eclectic reader (McGuffey, William Holmes); Lee, Robert E. (Robert Edward), 1807-1870; Nelson, Alexander Lockhart, 1827-1910; McGuffey, William Holmes, 1800-1873; Washington College (Lexington, Va.); University of Virginia
    - Correspondences, 1866-04-02 (Box 7A, Folder 51)
      - Wilmer McLean to Robert E. Lee, 1866-04-02 (Box 7A, Folder 51)
        This letter to Robert E. Lee is from Wilmer McLean. McLean asks Lee if he would come back to Appamatox to have a photograph of him taken in the room where he surrendered to General Ulysses S. Grant a year before.
        McLean House (Appomattox County, Va.); Lee, Robert E. (Robert Edward), 1807-1870; McLean, Wilmer, 1814-1882
      - Ellen Reily to Robert E. Lee, 1866-04-02; Reily, Ellen Hart, b. ca. 1814 (Box 7A, Folder 51)
        This letter to Robert E. Lee comes from Ellen Reily. She asks Lee if he could include her husband in his book on the American Civil War. She includes newspaper clippings, orders, and letters by and about her husband Colonel James Reily.
        Lee, Robert E. (Robert Edward), 1807-1870; Reily, James, 1811-1863; Mason, Emily V. (Emily Virginia), 1815-1909; Confederate States of America. Army. Sibley Brigade; The Houston Telegraph
    - Correspondences, 1866-04-03-1866-04-08 (Box 7A, Folder 52)
      - Elizabeth Hull to Robert E. Lee, 1866-04-05 (Box 7A, Folder 52)
        This letter to Robert E. Lee is from Elizabeth (referred to as Lizzie in the letter) Hull. She asks for information about Washington College for her adopted child.
        Lee, Robert E. (Robert Edward), 1807-1870; Hull, Edward Bordie, Jr., 1839-1921; Washington College (Lexington, Va.)
    - Correspondences, 1866-04-09-1866-04-10 (Box 7A, Folder 53)
      - Algernon Sidney Vigus to Robert E. Lee, 1866-04-09; Vigus, Algernon Sidney, c.1808-d.1873 (Box 7A, Folder 53)
        This letter to Robert E. Lee is from Algernon Sidney Vigus. Vigus has acquired Lee family letters that were taken from his home in Arlington, VA. He would like to give them back and asks how he would like them presented. One of the letters, to a Custis family member from London in 1728, is mentioned specifically. Vigus wishes to keep the letter if not important to Lee. Lee received all of the letters and mailed back the one from 1728.
        Arlington House, the Robert E. Lee Memorial (Va.); Lee, Robert E. (Robert Edward), 1807-1870; Custis, George Washington Parke, 1781-1857; Lee, Mary Randolph Custis, 1807-1883
      - H. McLeavy to Robert E. Lee, 1866-04-09 (Box 7A, Folder 53)
        This letter to Robert E. Lee is from H. McLeavy. McLeavy, a third-year of Soule University, wishes to attend Washington College for his fourth year. He also states that he served in the Confederate Army during the American Civil War and some of the classes he has taken.
        Lee, Robert E. (Robert Edward), 1807-1870; Soule University; Washington College (Lexington, Va.)
      - Hezekiah George David Brown to Robert E. Lee, 1866-04-09; Brown, Hezekiah George David (H. G. D.), 1824-1877 (Box 7A, Folder 53)
        This letter to Robert E. Lee is from Hezekiah George David (H. G. D.) Brown. Brown wishes to send his son to Washington College. He states that his son served in the Confederate Army during the American Civil War and was paroled in Alabama.
        Lee, Robert E. (Robert Edward), 1807-1870; Washington College (Lexington, Va.)
      - Charles Wesley Andrews to Robert E. Lee, 1866-04-09; Andrews, C. W. (Charles Wesley), 1807-1875 (Box 7A, Folder 53)
        This letter to Robert E. Lee is from Charles Wesley Andrews. Andrews contacts Lee for a few different reasons. The first is a life update that his wife, Sarah, died in 1863. He then asks for two photographs of Lee with his autograph, one of them for his daughter. Andrews also enclosed a pamphlet that he recently published. Finally he asks for Lee to tell his wife Mary that her cousin Anny's husband has made $90.00 in the past year.
        Virginia--Berryville; Lee, Robert E. (Robert Edward), 1807-1870; Andrews, Sarah Walker (Page), 1811-1863
      - Thomas L. Brown to Robert E. Lee, 1866-04-09 (Box 7A, Folder 53)
        This letter to Robert E. Lee comes from Thomas L. Brown. This letter accompanied a report by Brown of the Coal River Navigation Company which he hopes will take interest in minerals found in Virginia.
        West Virginia--Coal River (River); Lee, Robert E. (Robert Edward), 1807-1870; Coal River Navigation Company
      - Benjamin S. Elliott to Robert E. Lee, 1866-04-10; Elliott, Benjamin S., 1830-1884 (Box 7A, Folder 53)
        This letter to Robert E. Lee is from Benjamin S. Elliott. Elliott wishes to give Lee a Colt of the horse Patrick Henry. Included with this letter is a Carte de visite of Patrick Henry.
        Related Materials
        For Benjamin S. Elliott's later correspondence with Lee, see his letter from April 27, 1866 in Folder 56.
        Black Hawk (Horse) (1833-1856); Patrick Henry (Horse); Morgan horse; Carte de visite photographs; Photography -- Printing processes -- Albumen; Lee, Robert E. (Robert Edward), 1807-1870; Hill, David Edgar, 1819-1873; Silver Sunbeam Photography Studio
      - Rev. Robert S. Clark to Robert E. Lee, 1866-04-10; Clark, Robert S., Rev. (Box 7A, Folder 53)
        This letter to Robert E. Lee is from Reverend Robert S. Clark. Clark asks for the rights to publish Lee's history of the American Civil War in different counties of Mississippi.
        Mississippi--Attala County; Mississippi--Holmes County; Mississippi--Choctaw County; Mississippi--Carroll County; Mississippi--Yazoo County; Mississippi--Leake County; Mississippi--Winston County; Mississippi--Madison County; Lee, Robert E. (Robert Edward), 1807-1870; The National Star; Turner, George Paul; Davis, William Van, 1828-1884; Confederate States of America. Army. Mississippi Infantry Regiment, 30th; Ellert, W., Captain; Sallis, P. G., M.D.; Gossing, Sam, Captain
      - William H. Hope to Robert E. Lee, 1866-04-10; Hope, William H. (Box 7A, Folder 53)
        This letter to Robert E. Lee is from William H. Hope. Hope, a land lawyer in Virginia, wishes to represent Lee in gaining his Arlington estate back. He includes a newspaper clipping that union bodies will be dug from battlefields of the American Civil War and placed in Arlington.
        See the letter from Hope dated March 22nd, 1866 in folder 49.
        Arlington National Cemetery (Arlington, Va.); Arlington House, the Robert E. Lee Memorial (Va.); Clippings (Books, newspapers, etc.); Lee, Robert E. (Robert Edward), 1807-1870
      - Charles B. Richardson to Robert E. Lee, 1866-04-10; Richardson, Charles B. (Box 7A, Folder 53)
        This letter to Robert E. Lee comes from Charles B. Richardson. Richardson plans to donate $1,000 in books to the library of Washington College. He also says he will publish Lee's father's memoir once the family portraits arrive for engraving.
        See Charles B. Richardson's earlier letter to Robert E. Lee written March 20th, 1866 in folder 49.
        Libraries and colleges; Lee, Robert E. (Robert Edward), 1807-1870
      - Alexander Gardner to Robert E. Lee, 1866-04-10 (Box 7A, Folder 53)
        This letter to Robert E. Lee comes from Alexander Gardner. A portion of Gardner's Carte de visite photographs did not arrive to Lee. To make up for this, Gardner is sending photographs that are on hand at the studio with his imprint. He also plans to make and mount one-hundred photographs without his imprint.
        Photography; War photography; Carte de visite photographs; Lee, Robert E. (Robert Edward), 1807-1870; Gardner, Alexander, 1821-1882; Philp & Solomon; Gardner's Photographic Art Gallery
    - Correspondences, 1866-04-11-1866-04-14 (Box 7A, Folder 54)
      - Lemuel Parker Conner to Robert E. Lee, 1866-04-11; Conner, Lemuel Parker, 1827-1891 (Box 7A, Folder 54)
        This letter to Robert E. Lee comes from Lemuel Parker Conner. Conner is giving this letter to Robert E. Lee through his nephew William C. Conner, introducing him to Lee.
        Lee, Robert E. (Robert Edward), 1807-1870; Conner, William C.
      - John O. Sullivan to Robert E. Lee, 1866-04-11; Sullivan, John O. (Box 7A, Folder 54)
        John O. Sullivan asks Lee for catalogues of Washington College for some of his students who wish to attend.
        Tennessee--Fayetteville; Tennessee--Lincoln County; Washington College (Lexington, Va.)
      - S. P. Cunningham to Robert E. Lee, 1866-04-12; Cunningham, S. P. (Box 7A, Folder 54)
        S. P. Cunningham wants to obtain Washington College catalogues for Fairview Academy students wanting to attend.
        Virginia -- Richmond; Kentucky--Sharpsburg; Kentucky--Bath County; Lee, Robert E. (Robert Edward), 1807-1870; Washington College (Lexington, Va.); Davis, Jefferson, 1808-1889; Fairview Academy; Department of Western Kentucky
      - Warren Newcomb to Robert E. Lee, 1866-04-12; Newcomb, Warren, 1814-1866 (Box 7A, Folder 54)
        Newcomb, after making a donation to Washington College, clarifies that he was born in Massachussetts, not in the south and requests a photograph of Lee.
        Massachusetts--Franklin County; Louisiana -- New Orleans; Newcomb, R. E., Judge; Warren, Joseph, 1741-1775; Roman, André Bienvenu, 1795-1866
      - William Andrew Quarles to Robert E. Lee, 1866-04-12; Quarles, William Andrew, 1825-1893 (Box 7A, Folder 54)
        This letter to Robert E. Lee is from William Andrew Quarles. Quarles wishes to send his son to Washington College and asks for a catalog. He notes that his son is in Canada but made his way to Lieutenant in the Confederate Army during the American Civil War.
        Virginia -- Lexington; Tennessee--Clarksville; Lee, Robert E. (Robert Edward), 1807-1870; Venable, Charles S. (Charles Scott), 1827-1900; Holiday, Alexander; University of Virginia; Washington College (Lexington, Va.)
      - Edward Payson Walton to Robert E. Lee, 1866-04-13; Walton, Edward Payson, Reverend, 1829-1900 (Box 7A, Folder 54)
        This letter to Robert E. Lee is from Edward Payson Walton. Walton has been informed by Carter James Harris, professor of latin at Washington College, that Lee has taken offense to rumours published by Walton. Walton writes to Lee as an apology for any misunderstandings.
        Newspapers; Endowments; Lee, Robert E. (Robert Edward), 1807-1870; The Memphis Commercial; Washington College (Lexington, Va.); Harris, Carter James
      - James Kerr Caskie to Robert E. Lee, 1866-04-13; Caskie, James Kerr, 1818-1868 (Box 7A, Folder 54)
        This letter to Robert E. Lee comes from James Kerr Caskie. Caskie thanks Lee for his favors sent on the 7th and the 10th of Aprill 1866. Caskie is glad to hear that the vase and chair that he has sent are cherished. Caskie also tells Lee that his sister Agnes will be visiting Lexington, accompanied by Lee's son William Henry Fitzhugh Lee. On the other side of this letter is a balance of items bought. Caskie notes that he received 2 dozen photographs of Lee from Julian Vannerson but Vannerson would not accept money.
        Virginia--Ashland--Hickory Hill; War photography; Lee, Robert E. (Robert Edward), 1807-1870; Lee, Mary Anna Custis Randolph, 1807-1873; Lee, Mildred Childe, 1846-1905; Alexander, Agnes Caskie; Lee, William Henry Fitzhugh, 1837-1891; Vannerson, Julian, 1827-
      - Martin Luther Smith to Robert E. Lee, 1866-04-13; Smith, M. L. (Martin Luther), 1819-1866 (Box 7A, Folder 54)
        This letter to Robert E. Lee is from Martin Luther Smith. Smith writes to Lee after hearing that Washington College will be setting up a program for engineering. He asks if this school will be separate or a department and what books will be used.
        Engineering; Lee, Robert E. (Robert Edward), 1807-1870; Washington College (Lexington, Va.)
      - E. H. Campbell to Robert E. Lee, 1866-04-14; Campbell, E. H. (Box 7A, Folder 54)
        This letter to Robert E. Lee comes from E. H. Campbell, cordial secretary for the Charles Town Christian Association. Campbell informs Lee that he has been made an honorary member.
        West Virginia--Charles Town; Lee, Robert E. (Robert Edward), 1807-1870; Charles Town Christian Association
      - Clara Banks to Robert E. Lee, 1866-04-14; Banks, Clara (Box 7A, Folder 54)
        This letter to Robert E. Lee comes from Clara Banks of Liverpool, England. She writes to him asking for his autograph. Above the letter is her monogram which takes influence from illuminated manuscript lettering.
        Autographs; Monograms; England--Liverpool; Lee, Robert E. (Robert Edward), 1807-1870
      - Daniel Moreau Barringer to Robert E. Lee, 1866-04-14 (Box 7A, Folder 54)
        This letter to Robert E. Lee comes from Daniel Moreau Barringer. Barringer wishes to send his son Lewin to Washington College and is asking for a catalogue. He writes from Baltimore but instructs Lee that he lives in Raleigh, North Carolina.
        Maryland--Baltimore; North Carolina--Raleigh; Lee, Robert E. (Robert Edward), 1807-1870; Barringer, Lewin Wethered, 1850-1900; Washington College (Lexington, Va.)
    - Correspondences, 1866-04-16-1866-04-23 (Box 7A, Folder 55)
      - J. L. Greer to Robert E. Lee, 1866-04-16; Greer, J. L. (Box 7A, Folder 55)
        This letter to Robert E. Lee comes from J. L. Greer who wishes to send his brother to Washington College for his junior year. He asks for a catalogue so his brother can properly prepare.
        Georgia--West Point; Lee, Robert E. (Robert Edward), 1807-1870; Washington College (Lexington, Va.)
      - Oden Bowie to Robert E. Lee, 1866-04-17; Bowie, Oden, 1826-1894 (Box 7A, Folder 55)
        This letter to Robert E. Lee comes from Oden Bowie, Governor of Maryland. He asks Lee to send a catalogue for an aquaintance that wants to send someone to Washington College.
        Fairview Plantation
      - James Woods Smith to Robert E. Lee, 1866-04-17; Smith, James Woods (Box 7A, Folder 55)
        This letter to Robert E. Lee is from James Woods Smith. Smith plans to attend Washington College and asks for a catalogue and additional information to attend.
        Woods, Yeatman, & Co.
      - S. D. Rosan to Robert E. Lee, 1866-04-17; Rosan, S. D. (Box 7A, Folder 55)
        This letter to Robert E. Lee comes from S. D. Rosan. Rosan wishes to attend Washington College and asks for Lee to send a circular of the school.
        Maryland--Baltimore County--Catonsville--St. Timothy's Hall
      - Elizabeth S. Myrick to Robert E. Lee, 1866-04-18; Myrick, Elizabeth S. (Dowdell), 1824-1889 (Box 7A, Folder 55)
        This letter to Robert E. Lee comes from Elizabeth S. Myrick (writing as Mrs. S. P. Myrick). Elizabeth wishes to send her son, James, to Washington College and asks for a circular and requirements to attend. She explains that her son left school at fifteen to serve in the Civil War and fears his age and limited schooling before the war may hinder his opportunity to the school.
        Civil engineering; Myrick, James Dowdell, 1846-1910
      - Henry A. Barling to Robert E. Lee, 1866-04-20; Barling, Henry A. (Box 7A, Folder 55)
        This letter to Robert E. Lee comes from Henry A. Barling. Barling wishes for his nephew to attend Washington College and asks for a circular. He says his nephew has grown up in Georgia until late in the war and is currently attending school in Troy, New York. He also says that while his nephew is only fifteen he is very advanced in his studies.
        New York (State)--Troy; Georgia--Bainbridge; Tonge, Samuel D.
      - John Reynolds Winston to Robert E. Lee, 1866-04-20; Winston, John Reynolds, 1839-1888 (Box 7A, Folder 55)
        This letter to Robert E. Lee comes from John Reynolds Winston. Winston asks if Lee is writing a history of the American Civil War and urges him to do so.
      - John E. Matthews to Robert E. Lee, 1866-04-21; Matthews, John E. (Box 7A, Folder 55)
        Matthews explains that he left school during the Civil War to serve in the Confederate Army. To make up for loss time he wishes to attend Washington College. Matthews asks Lee for a circular and requirements to attend.
        Tennessee--Williamson County--College Grove
      - Henry F. Mayer to Robert E. Lee, 1866-04-21; Mayer, Henry F. (Box 7A, Folder 55)
        Mayer requests information on Washington College as he wishes to send his son to the school.
        United States--Mason-Dixon Line
      - James A. Mitchell to Robert E. Lee, 1866-04-23; Mitchell, James A. (Box 7A, Folder 55)
        This letter to Robert E. Lee comes from James A. Mitchell. Mitchell is interested in attending Washington College and would like catalogues sent for him and other potential students in Edmonton, Kentucky.
        Kentucky--Edmonton
    - Correspondences, 1866-04-24-1866-04-30 (Box 7A, Folder 56)
      - John Hough James to Robert E. Lee, 1866-04-24; James, John Hough, 1800-1881 (Box 7A, Folder 56)
        This letter to Robert E. Lee comes from John Hough James. James informs Lee that if he wishes to keep receiving the Urbana Union newspaper, he can resend the envelope this letter was enclosed in. If Lee does not wish to keep receiving this paper, he should send it back with a cross next to his name.
        American newspapers; Newspapers; Journalism; Lee, Robert E. (Robert Edward), 1807-1870; Urbana Union
      - George Lyttleton Peyton to Robert E. Lee, 1866-04-23; Peyton, George Lyttleton, 1829-1909 (Box 7A, Folder 56)
        This letter to Robert E. Lee comes from George Lyttleton Peyton. Peyton offers for Lee to come stay at the hotel.
        Virginia -- Staunton; Lee, Robert E. (Robert Edward), 1807-1870; Virginia Hotel
      - S. S. Louisa to Robert E. Lee, 1866-04-26; Cochrane, S. S. Louisa, 1820-1897 (Box 7A, Folder 56)
        This letter to Robert E. Lee comes from S. S. Louisa Cochrane. Cochrane hopes to send her son William G. "Gilly" Cochrane to Washington College and requests a catalogue or circular.
        Cochrane, William G. "Gilly", 1848-1913
      - Dominick James Dillon to Robert E. Lee, 1866-04-27; Dillon, Dominick James, 1825-1908 (Box 7A, Folder 56)
        This letter is addressed to Robert E. Lee from Dominick James Dillon.Dillon wishes to send his son to Washington College and is awaiting a catalogue.
      - Benjamin S. Elliott to Robert E. Lee, 1866-04-27; Elliott, Benjamin S., 1830-1884 (Box 7A, Folder 56)
        This letter to Robert E. Lee comes from Benjamin S. Elliott. Elliott informs Lee that he favor he asked for on the 24th of April, 1866 has been fulfilled. Although Lee did not accept Elliott's offer for Patrick Henry's colt, Elliott is negotating for a two-year-old colt to be given to Lee. This letter also contains its original envelope.
        For Benjamin S. Elliott's earlier correspondence with Lee, see his letter from April 10, 1866 in Folder 53.
        Patrick Henry (Horse); Morgan horse; Maryland--Harford County; Lee, Robert E. (Robert Edward), 1807-1870; Megan, R. L.
      - Unsigned note to Lee dated April 28th, 1866, 1866-04-28 (Box 7A, Folder 56)
        This note came with a package addressed to Robert E. Lee. The note explains a forwarded package meant for Lee from Algernon Sidney Vigus. The package contained books Vigus removed from the Lee family's "Arlington House" during the American Civil War.
        For context of this note, see Algernon Sidney Vigus' original letter to Lee dated April 9th, 1866 in folder 53.
        Arlington House, the Robert E. Lee Memorial (Va.); Vigus, Algernon Sidney, c.1808-d.1873
      - Walter Hanson Jenifer to Robert E. Lee, 1866-04-28; Jenifer, Walter Hanson, 1823-1878 (Box 7A, Folder 56)
        This letter was written by Walter Hanson Jenifer to Robert E. Lee. Jenifer writes that he has decided to retire from cavalry service and is now part of a business. He offers his services to Lee if he ever needs them. Included with this letter is an advertisement for Jenifer's business, "Jenifer and Brother".
        Cavalry; Jenifer & Brother General Purchasing and Sale Agency; Confederate States of America. Army. Virginia Cavalry Regiment, 8th
      - Chestley Netterville to Robert E. Lee, 1866-04-29; Netterville, Chestley, 1847-1924 (Box 7A, Folder 56)
        This letter is written by Chestley Netterville to Robert E. Lee. Netterville wishes to attend Washington College in the fall of 1866 and would like a catalogue.
      - John C. Breckinridge to Robert E. Lee, 1866-04-29 (Box 7A, Folder 56)
        This letter by John Cabell Breckinridge is to Robert E. Lee. Breckinridge asks for Lee to keep an eye and advise three brothers, William, James, and Edward Carson, attending Washington College. He also has heard that Lee is planning to write about the American Civil War campaigns in Virginia but that he has little written material to share.
        Carson, William Waller, 1845-1930; Carson, James Green, Jr., 1847-1887; Carson, Edward Lees, 1848-1905; Lees, Catharine Waller, 1815-1888; Carson family
      - S. G. Landes to Robert E. Lee, 1866-04-30; Landes, S. G. (Box 7A, Folder 56)
        This letter by S. G. Landes is addressed to Robert E. Lee. He asks Lee to sign an autograph on a blank page included with this letter. He writes this letter from Mt. Carmel, Illinois although he notes that he grew up in the Rockbridge and Augusta counties of Virginia.
        Autographs; Virginia -- Augusta County; Virginia -- Rockbridge County; Illinois--Mount Carmel; Lee, Robert E. (Robert Edward), 1807-1870
      - Strobridge & Co. to Robert E. Lee, 1866-04-30; Strobridge Lithographing Company (Box 7A, Folder 56)
        This letter by the Strobridge Lithography Company is addressed to Robert E. Lee. The letter references lithographs of Robert E. Lee. The company apologizes for a delay in delivery of one example explaining that fire had destroyed its Cincinnati studio, including that Lee lithograph portrait. They share that a third lithograph is in process as well as a portrait of Stonewall Jackson.
        Pike's Opera House; Portrait prints; Lithography; Jackson, Stonewall, 1824-1863
    - Correspondences, 1866-05-01-1866-05-04 (Box 7A, Folder 57)
      - F. Bullwinkle to Robert E. Lee, 1866-05-01; Bullwinkle, F. (Box 7A, Folder 57)
        This letter by F. Bullwinkle is for Robert E. Lee. Bullwinkle wishes to get a mathematical education from Washington College and would like a catalogue.
        Agricultural colleges; Pennsylvania--Centre County
      - Stonewall Literary Society to Robert E. Lee, 1866-05-01 (Box 7A, Folder 57)